Chapter 7

I had a long talk with Jenkinson that night in the library and put him in possession of the facts of this affair, so far as they were known to me. He sat listening to me in silence for the most part, detached, critical, alert. Now and again he interpolated a searching little question, but not frequently. At the end of it he removed his pince–nez and sat polishing them upon his handkerchief.

“There should not be any great difficulty,” he said at last. “We must try and persuade the young lady to give a statement to the police tomorrow. They are entitled to that assistance in their investigations. Under certain safeguards, both for herself and for her brother….”

He replaced his glasses. “Safeguards. I must think out the safeguards which we can impose.”

I gave him a whisky and we went to bed.

We had a conference in the library next morning after breakfast. Mollie was there, a little awed by the presence of the lawyer. Perhaps in deference to him she had made herself a bit less ornamental for the occasion; her eyelashes remained unwaxed, and in some subtle manner she had made herself look quieter than before. It may have been that she had less makeup on, it may have been that she was simply blending into the surrounding of my house. I don’t know. I only know that I had expected Jenkinson to have something of a shock when he saw what I’d picked up, but it was I who got the shock.

He began by explaining to her again the position that she was in. In his precise, rather meticulous way he outlined to her the inquiry which the Criminal Investigation Department had in hand, acting on behalf of the Civil Power. He showed her that so far the whole of the evidence available tended to the implication that her brother must be involved in business directed towards the provocation of a breach of the peace, if nothing more serious. He said that he had to point out to her the gravity of the situation in that respect, but would emphasize that there should be no necessity for undue alarm about her brother. Similar cases had occurred during the Irish troubles, and he cited one or two cases in which the clemency of the crown had been directed in favour of persons who were in a similar position in being subordinate to the main issue. He made a point there, that such clemency was only exerted in those cases where a genuine desire to assist the processes of the Law was assured. At the outset of this matter, his advice was to the effect that she should give him authority to express to the police her utmost willingness to assist them in their investigation.

“I am sure that we shall find that this matter will go quite smoothly if we can give them that assurance, Miss Gordon,” he said, and paused for her reply.

She was troubled. “I don’t quite understand,” she said at last. “I’m for Billy. Is that what you wanted me to say?”

I laughed. “No, it’s not,” I said. “We want you to tell the police all you know about Billy.”

She stared at me in perplexity. “But then they’d catch him,” she objected.

We moistened the lips and started again, and for a quarter of an hour I explained to her in as simple language as I could the position that her brother must be in, and what we wanted to do about it. She came to understand it in the end, I think.

“You mean that’s really the best thing for me to do for Billy?” she inquired. “Just tell them all about him?”

Jenkinson interposed: “Perhaps not quite everything. They may ask questions that they have no right to ask, and I would not let you answer those. We shall both be there to help you answer every question, so there will be nothing to be afraid of. Just tell the whole truth when they ask you anything. I’ll stop you saying anything that you ought not to say.”

She turned to me: “You don’t think he’ll be sent to prison? You see, he wouldn’t be doing anything bad.”

I said: “We don’t know what he is doing. But I’ll promise you this. If any proceedings are taken against him, he shall have the best legal defence in the country. We’ll brief Sir Dennis Scott–Neil for him, or somebody like that.”

She eyed me searchingly. “You wouldn’t let me down?”

I met her eyes. “I won’t let you down,” I said. “This really is the best thing to do.”

She nodded gravely, and turned to Jenkinson. “Please,” she said, “you’ll have to tell me when to speak and when not to. You see, I don’t know about these things.”

I glanced at Jenkinson, and he glanced back at me, and after a moment we went on with her examination. Together we asked her what questions we could think of, to prepare ourselves for what she might be going to tell the police, but we found very little that I didn’t know. She knew that her brother had been working on an all–night job, she thought intermittently, for about a couple of months. She could give no further indication as to how to get in touch with him. She thought he was well paid, but who paid him she did not know. She was quite sure he wouldn’t do anything wrong.

We came to an end of all she knew quite soon. After a short talk with Jenkinson I crossed the room and rang up Fedden at his house.

“Good–morning,” I said. “Stevenson speaking. About this statement that you want to get from Miss Gordon. I’ve got Jenkinson down here, and we’ve just been through it all with her. Miss Gordon is quite ready to tell you all she knows, under the guidance of her solicitor of course.”

He said: “I’m very glad to hear that. Norman will be back by lunchtime; we’ll take her statement this afternoon. I see no point in taking it at Newton Abbot. Will you bring her down to the police station here, at three o’clock?”

I pressed the transmitter to my chest and shot a rapid question at Jenkinson. “Certainly,” he said, “that would be quite in order.”

I lifted the transmitter. “I’ll do nothing of the sort,” I said curtly. “Miss Gordon will see you here, in the library of my house, at two o’clock precisely, if you please.”

He said: “That’s most unusual, you know.”

“Miss Gordon had a bad time in your police station yesterday,” I replied, “and I’m damned if she’s going there again. I should like to think that that was most unusual. This is a purely voluntary statement on her part, and if you want it she is willing to give it to you at two o’clock this afternoon. Her solicitor will be present, and you can bring this Major Norman.” I smiled. “I’m willing to sink my prejudices so far as to admit him to my house, on this occasion only. I should like to make that point quite clear.”

He said stiffly: “I understand that perfectly. Very well. You can expect us at two o’clock this afternoon.”

He rang off, and I turned to Jenkinson. “Glad I’m not a Chief Constable,” I said.

There was nothing more that we could do until they came. We went out into the garden; Jenkinson lives at Chislehurst and goes to his office every day in an electric train, and grows begonias and things like that, and takes prizes for them at the local flower show. He is a member of the Royal Horticultural Society, I think; I only know he got me properly tied up, so that I had to get old Robertson out of his hot houses to answer some of the questions that he asked. Together we went round the rose garden, a little absently on my part. I was thinking about what would be necessary for Sweet Anna; we had given her a new mainsail in the previous autumn, but topsails and mizzen were getting very thin. I had a long talk with Tillotson next day, and we decided that she ought to have them. We gave her a new second jib, as well.

In the garden Mollie got on well with Jenkinson; he found in her an eager audience for his rather arid little discourses upon begonias. I had one or two things that I wanted to do in the town that day—I forget what they were at the moment. Those two were getting on quite well together and so I left them to it and went down to the town, wondering as I went what questions she would ask him about me. She wouldn’t get much out of Jenkinson, I thought. He’s too cautious.

I got back home a little late for lunch. They had waited for me, and that made the whole programme late, so that before we had finished lunch Fedden and Norman had arrived. It amused me to send out Rogers to show them into the library and to keep them waiting while we sat and drank our coffee in the dining–room. I had a score to settle with those gentlefolk.

That wasn’t the only thing they had to put up with that afternoon. We went into the library and settled down at the big centre table there, and Jenkinson led off with a sour, legal little speech. In his dry way he informed them that he was acting on behalf of both Miss Gordon and her brother, and would continue to do so. He understood that an examination of Miss Gordon had already been attempted in circumstances which appeared to him to have been most irregular. He trusted that he would have no occasion to complain of any further irregularity of that sort. He quite understood that their business was the detection of crime. His own business was the preservation of the integrity of the Law. It would be unfortunate if in the pursuance of their business they again ran contrary to his own.

He let them ask some questions then. They had brought a police sergeant with them who took notes, and we sat for some time while they questioned the girl, and this chap took his notes in longhand. She gave her answers pretty well, prompted and assisted every now and then by Jenkinson.

I forget how it all went, and what they asked. I only know that none of it was new. They asked nothing that was not obvious, and they discovered nothing that we had not known before. The girl was quite incapable of assisting them to find her brother; she had not the remotest notion where he was. She could only suggest that her people up in Preston might know something of his movements, but she didn’t think it likely that they would. We sat there for most of the afternoon, and so far as I could see it was an utter waste of time.

It finished up at last; the sergeant closed his notebook and they got up to go. Jenkinson gave them a final word of warning. He told them that he was definitely employed on behalf of Mr William Gordon, and that no statements should be taken from that gentleman, or evidence of any sort, until he had been informed that a solicitor had been engaged on his behalf, and had consulted him.

They went away at last, and we went out to tea upon the terrace looking out over the harbour. I would have asked Fedden to stay, but Norman and the sergeant were with him and I felt I’d had my fill of the CID for the time being.

Jenkinson wanted to catch an evening train back to town. When Rogers brought the tea I sent him to look up trains; it was a warm, sunny afternoon and we sat for a long time over tea, looking out over the rose garden below. We were all a little relieved, I think, that nothing untoward had come out during the afternoon, and glad that it was over. Mollie and Jenkinson were gossiping away together like old friends, and I remember that he was very decent to her in telling her that she was to come to him in case of any further difficulty, whether she was staying with me or not.

His train went from Newton Abbot. I drove him there in the Bentley, leaving Mollie sitting on the terrace; she said that she was tired. I think that may have been tact upon her part. It gave me the opportunity of a word or two with Jenkinson, and I explained to him a little more fully the circumstances in which I had got her down from Leeds, as we drove.

He nodded. “A girl of a good type,” he said.

I was silent for a minute. “I’ve lived very much among my own sort all my life,” I said at last. “It’s not a very common type, is it?”

He shrugged his shoulders. “I think you get that quiet, refined sort of girl in every class. I used to see quite a lot of them in police work when I was a young man. Shop assistants, typists—girls of every class. You meet a good few barmaids of that sort. Do you see much of them?”

I shook my head. “I don’t go into bars much. A man like me has to guard against that sort of thing.”

He smiled. “I don’t know what’s happening to the classes in this country,” he said. “One comes on girls like this so frequently—and a good few men, too. The only difference between them and us is that they don’t know quite so many facts…. Behaviour’s just the same. And that’s a mighty small difference….”

I put him into his train at Newton Abbot, thanked him for coming down, and saw him off. Then I went back to Dartmouth to my house. I found Mollie in the library; rather to my surprise I saw her sitting curled up upon the chesterfield reading a large book. She laid it down carefully as I came in, and got up to meet me.

“We got that train all right,” I said, and glanced down to see what it was that she had been reading. It was Mortimer’s Naval History, open at the page which describes the action of the Jane Ellen. I glanced at the bookshelves, and there was a gap where she had got the volume from.

“So you’ve got hold of that,” I said.

She looked up at me, and nodded; and then she said: “Tell me, was this really you?” She stooped and picked up the book. “I mean, in here.”

I took the book from her and glanced down the account a little absently; she came closer and looked over my elbow at the page. “Yes,” I said at last, “that was me. Doesn’t seem much like it now, does it?”

“I think it’s wonderful,” she breathed. And then she looked up at me and said; “Mr Jenkinson showed it me. You don’t mind, do you?”

I smiled at her. “Lord, no,” I said. “Not after all these years. It’s all so long ago.”

She stood there staring up at me, puzzled. “Don’t you like people to know about it? I mean, it says here it was all so splendid, and you got a medal.”

“There wasn’t anything splendid about it, really,” I said quietly. “Only in the history books. It was just bloody murder.”

She stared up at me dumbly.

“I shelled them while they were surrendering,” I said. “The engagement was over by that time.” I stared out of the window at the brilliant, sunlit sea. “I don’t know why I did it—I never did know. There was a boy there with me, a midshipman. He wouldn’t speak to me when we got back to land—just cut me dead whenever we met. The funny thing is, I don’t think he told anyone.”

I paused. “When you go and do a thing like that it makes a difference,” I said. A herring gull came sweeping down the lawn and banked steeply past the window in the sunshine with a little cry. I stood there thinking of the long, similar years that I had lived in Dartmouth since the war, living alone with my ships and with my work. “Things haven’t been much fun since I did that,” I said quietly. “Not like they were before.”

I glanced down at her. “Not so very splendid, was it?”

She looked up at me, and then down at the book. “I think it was wonderful,” she said at last. “Fighting on all alone like that. Nobody could have said anything if you’d given in, could they? I mean, when there was only three of you left.”

I laughed. “It wouldn’t have done us much good to give in. They shelled the panic party in the boats. We wouldn’t have stood much chance in a surrender, and so we just stuck where we were.”

She wrinkled up her brows. “You mean that they’d have killed you if you’d given in?”

I shrugged my shoulders. “I dare say. They’d probably have left us out on deck when they submerged.”

She came a little closer to me. “Malcolm,” she said, and it was the first time she had called me that, “you oughtn’t to think so much about the bad things of the war. I mean, everyone who fought had to do bad things, and it was the same on each side. And you only did to them what they’d have done to you if you’d surrendered.”

I stood for a moment looking down at her. “That may be,” I said. “But it was I who did it.”

I was touched by the insight that she had shown; I had never been able to speak to anyone about that business as I had to her. She didn’t say any more, and I took her by the arm and we wandered out into the garden for a quarter of an hour before going in to dress. Passing the strawberry bed we stopped and ate a few, and together we picked a few more flowers for her room, although she said the ones she had would last for ‘ever so long’. She told me how she used to make flowers last in the Palais when she wore them in her dress with their stalks wrapped up in cotton wool and silver paper and they kept ever so fresh for days.

Then we went up to dress.

And coming down, I found she was before me in the hall. She had changed into the same blue dancing frock with the silver bodice that she had worn before, that suited her dark loveliness so well. She came up to me as I walked down the stairs, and:

“Please, Commander Stevenson,” she said, and hesitated.

I smiled at her. “Spit it out,” I said.

She didn’t laugh, but looked up at me. “Please,” she said, “I’ve just been thinking. Now that Mr Jenkinson’s gone and the police and everything, I’d better go back to Leeds. I thought I’d go by train tomorrow morning, if that would be all right. I mean, you won’t be wanting me for anything else now, will you?”

For a moment I was nonplussed. “No,” I said mechanically, “I don’t know that there’s anything else, really.”

She stood there looking up at me, dumbly. I moved closer to her and took one of her hands in mine; we stood there together, looking down at it. “You can go if you like, of course,” I said. “But won’t you stay and have your holiday with me? I’d like it awfully if you would.”

She didn’t look at me. “Are you sure you really want me here?” she said. “Don’t you think I’d be in the way, with all your friends, and that?”

I shook my head. “I meant it when I asked you to come down here for your holiday, that night in Leeds. It was useful for the police, but that was only half. I meant it for you as well.”

She raised her head; she had got a colour, and her eyes were very bright. “You mean you really want me to stay the whole time?” she said. “Six more days?”

“Of course I do,” I said. “If it’s not too dull for you.”

She sighed happily. “It’s all so perfect here. It’s going to be the loveliest holiday I’ve ever had.” She rippled into laughter. “Won’t Ethel be jealous when I tell her!” Ethel was her friend who had gone to Scarborough. “And she’ll never believe me when I tell her I’ve been good.”

I laughed and took her arm. “I don’t suppose she will,” I said. And so we went and dined.

I forget what we talked about at dinner that night; I only remember that the telephone bell rang in the middle of it. I left the table and went to it in the library, and it was Joan speaking from her house in Golders Green.

“Is that Malcolm?”

“Speaking,” I said.

“Oh, Malcolm—this is Joan this end.” I said something polite. “What I rang you up about was this: can we come down and spend the night with you tomorrow—me and Philip? We’ve got a couple of days for the Irene, and Philip wants to have a talk with you. Oh, just one minute, he’s here.”

Stenning came to the telephone. “Evening, Stevenson; I say, is it you who’s been putting the CID on my track again? I had a fellow called Norman call to see me two or three days ago—wanted to know all sorts of things. He said I’d told you, or something. Yes, I met him once before—not a bad cove, is he?” I sometimes think that Stenning must know everybody in the world. “Well, what I thought was this: Joan and I might come down in time for dinner tomorrow night, and we’d have a chat about it before going off in the Irene. How’s that?”

“Quite all right,” I replied. “You won’t be able to have your usual room, though. You’ll have to put up with single ones.”

He asked: “Why’s that?”

Some things can hardly be explained over the telephone. I said: “It’s occupied.”

I heard him laugh. “I remember when I was a young man I used to live in sin a bit myself,” he said genially. There was a scuffling noise at the other end; I could imagine Joan throwing a cushion at him. “That’s all right, old boy—we quite understand.” I smiled; he had an uncanny flair for hitting near the mark. “All right, we’ll be down in time for dinner. Can I land in Thompson’s field?”

“I expect so. I’ll get him to clear that shed. It’s a Moth, isn’t it?”

“That’s right,” he said. “All right, I’ll see you then.”

I hung up the receiver and went back to Mollie in the dining room. “That was my cousin and her husband,” I told her. “Speaking from London. They’re coming down here to spend the night tomorrow.”

She stared at me in alarm. “Coming here?”

I nodded. “I think you’ll like them.”

She waited till Rogers was out of the room, then bent towards me. “Please, Commander Stevenson,” she said, “don’t you think I’d better not be here when your cousins come?” She paused for a moment. “I mean, it looks so funny for you.”

I laughed. “Not half so funny as it does for you.”

She smiled. “I don’t mind a bit about me. But, I mean, it looks so awful for you with your friends, having a strange girl in the house, and everything.”

I buttered a bit of toast. “If my friends don’t like the way I carry on they needn’t come,” I said phlegmatically. “I’d rather have the strange girl, myself,” I paused. “As a matter of fact, you don’t need to worry about these people—really. They’ll only be here for the one night, and you’ll like Joan.”

She asked me: “What’s their name?”

“Stenning,” I said, “Sir Philip and Lady Stenning. I expect you’ve heard about him, haven’t you? The flying man.”

She stared at me, wide–eyed. “I saw him on the pictures once. Is he your cousin?”

“His wife is. Lady Stenning is my cousin Joan.”

“Oh—” She thought about it for a minute, and then she said: “Don’t you think I’d better just go away while they’re here? I mean, I’m sure Lady Stenning will think it awfully funny, won’t she?” She said: “I could just go down and stay in the town till they’ve gone.”

“If you talk like that,” I said, “I’ll ring up and say they can’t come.”

She laughed and said I mustn’t do that, and we went on with dinner, but I could see that she was not at ease. She talked carefully, and a little absent mindedly, about unimportant things, but said no more about it till the table was cleared and we rose to go into the other room. In the hall she hesitated.

“Please,” she said, “I’ve only got this evening frock, you know, and it’s two years old.” She looked down at it critically. “It’s terribly grubby. Do you think it will be all right for Lady Stenning?”

I smiled. I think she thought that Joan would look at her through a lorgnette, and that Stenning would wear a morningcoat and talk about the League. “I wouldn’t worry about that,” I said. “They’re flying down, so they won’t bring much stuff. I don’t suppose Joan will want to change at all. And anyway, she hasn’t got a dinner frock that’s a patch on that one.”

She beamed. “I’m glad you like me in it,” she said. “It was awfully pretty, but it’s an old thing now.”

We went into the library and had our coffee sitting on the chesterfield, and over it she told me how she had had that dress in the first instance for a speciality dance she used to do when she was in a Palais in Manchester, and she told me how she had altered it to make it into a dinner frock. And from that we went on talking about dancing and music, till at last I said: “Wouldn’t you like to play the piano a bit tonight? I’d like it awfully if you would.”

She looked very doubtful. “I don’t play very well, and I haven’t got any of my pieces here. I don’t think I could play anything except dance tunes out of my head. You wouldn’t care so much about those, would you?”

“Rather,” I said. “Play Body and Soul.”

She laughed, and slipped over to the piano. I sat over on the other side of the room with my cigar while she crashed into the jazz melody; she played well, with a spirit and energy which made up in that sort of music for her occasional slips. I moved to a chair nearer the piano and presently, warming to her work, she began to sing the words.

She had a trained voice, and for a time I wondered where she had got it from, until I remembered her early training for the chorus. That night she sang those dance songs with a naïve feeling that robbed them of all crudity and gave them a new interpretation to me. She showed them to me as the folk songs of the people that I know so little of, the working England and America that I scarcely knew. I sat there thinking how much I had lived apart since the war, that I knew so little of her side of life.

The night closed down about us and I lit a reading lamp above her piano. She sat there fingering the keys and talking to me about the songs and dances that she knew, showing me the snap and rhythm of the airs, telling me the steps for each. That subject was peculiarly her own. From the semi–darkness of the hall I sat and watched her at the piano, the slim lines of her neck and shoulders merging gently into the silver bodice of her dress. She had gained a colour from her pleasure in the music; in the soft light I saw that she was very beautiful.

And presently she said: “Oh, and I know another one. I do think this is pretty; it comes out of a play called Bitter Sweet. It’s sort of different to the rest of them.” She played the fox trot air for a few minutes, and then sang quietly:

“I believe in doing what I can,
In crying when I must,
In laughing when I choose.
Heigh–ho, if love were all
I should be lonely!
I believe the more you love a man,
The more you give your trust,
The more you’re bound to lose—
Although, when shadows fall
I think if only
Somebody splendid really needed me,
Someone affectionate and dear—
Cares would be ended if I knew that he
Wanted to have me near….”

I sat there very quiet, listening to her; she had grown absorbed in her song. It seemed to me that I was listening to something more than a scene out of a revue, that I was listening to a confession of the philosophy which guided her among the various hazards of the life she had to live. I felt that she was paying me a singular honour in singing that to me, perhaps unconsciously.

Her voice died away into the lonely silence of my house. She dropped her fingers from the keys and sat there motionless. “That was very beautiful,” I said.

She turned to me, her eyes shining in the dim light. “You mean you really thought that?—that it was nice?”

I stirred a little in my chair. “It suited you,” I said.

She sat there gazing down at me, not quite understanding what I meant. “It’s my favourite,” she said at last. “It is pretty, isn’t it?”

She got up and closed the piano; with that song she had finished singing for the night. I crossed to the side table where they leave my nightcap. “You’d like a drink after all that singing,” I suggested. “What would you like?” I eyed the table. “There’s whisky here—and lemonade. Would you like a gin and tonic?”

She hesitated. “Do you know what I’d like—if it wouldn’t be a dreadful trouble?”

I paused. “What’s that?”

“A cup of tea.”

I rang the bell and ordered tea, and we went through into the model room. By the Jane Ellen model case she stopped. “Was this the ship?” she asked.

I nodded. “That was the ship.”

She stood there looking at the model for a long time, very still, one hand resting on the case. And then: “It was a splendid thing,” she said.

I couldn’t argue it, and so I let her have her way. I moved over to the window. “Tomorrow we’ll go down to the yard,” I said. “I want to show you all my ships and things. And we’ve not bathed yet, either.”

She beamed. “I’ve got ever such a lovely bathing dress that I got last autumn in the sales. I haven’t worn it yet—only in my bedroom before the glass. I was keeping it for my holiday.” She paused. “It’s a lovely colour—sort of apple green.”

She looked best in green; all the girls said so. So she had told me. “It sounds all right,” I said.

She dimpled. “You may not like me in it.”

“I expect I shall,” I said comfortably. And so we sat there in the half–light looking out over the harbour, and gossiped, and drank our tea till it was time to go to bed. That night, for the first time since my accident, I slept soundly and dreamlessly till I was called at eight o’clock.

I saw Mollie in the garden that morning while I was shaving, coming up from the fuzzy. She had been down to have another look at the bathing place; so she told me while we were breakfasting. She was itching to go in.

I’d have taken her down to bathe at once, since she seemed to be so keen, but I had to go down to the yard that morning for an horn or so. I made her a promise that we’d bathe before lunch; she was content, and as we breakfasted she told me about everything that she had seen on her morning’s walk—the birds and the flowers and the trees. She had been up at six. Spreading my toast and marmalade, it struck me that she wasn’t missing much.

We went down together to the yard; Sweet Anna was still lying out in the stream at anchor. I am a little short of quayside for the vessels undergoing a refit; I should like to build on, but it would cost a lot. That day there was a smack lying at the shore end of my quay and Pearl Maid at the outer end; we had been setting up her mizzen with new standing gear, so that there was a great smell of Stockholm tar all round the place. Entering the gates one can always tell what work is going on from the smell: paint, the bark we use for tanning sails, wood smoke, tar—all these in turn provide aroma for my yard.

Mollie came with me into the office, and sat quiet in a corner while I did my letters; I think it was a new experience to her. It was certainly a new one to the staff, and must have given them cause for gossip for a week or so. Miss Soames came in and took my letters and never raised an eyelid from her pad; Tillotson came in to talk about his cost accounts, but took no account of Sixpence sitting in her corner trying to read the Marine Transporter’s Journal and Monthly Advertiser. He went away, and I sent for Penhill to tell him that Irene was to be ready for Stenning by the evening and, as an afterthought, I told him that I should be wanting Runagate next day. Then a short talk with old Captain Sammy Gore, of Sweet Anna. He wanted new rudder pintles, or thought he did, but I think it was only because some rumour had reached him far away up on the north–east coast that we had given them to Mary Thompson at her last refit. I told him that Sweet Anna was a better built vessel than Mary Thompson, which was nearly true and matched his own belief, and that we’d have a look when she dried out.

Then the watchman came, as watchmen always do, to say that it wasn’t that he wasn’t willing, but he couldn’t work miracles, and he was doing three men’s work and not complaining, and he ought to have some help.

Then I was free to go and bathe.

I took Mollie out of the office and showed her something of my yard and ships. We didn’t stay very long because I knew she wanted to get back; that green bathing dress was pulling very strongly. However, I found that she was still worrying a little about Joan and Stenning, because she said, quite suddenly: “Please, Commander Stevenson, about this evening. When Lady Stenning comes, do you play cards—bridge, or anything? Because I’m afraid I couldn’t. I don’t know any card games hardly, except Sevens.”

I thought for a moment that I’d telephone to put them off, to tell them that they’d better sleep in the Irene for the night. And then I thought I wouldn’t. For some obscure reason I wanted Joan to meet her, and there was really nothing for her to be frightened of in meeting Joan. That wasn’t to say that I could prevent her being frightened. It was the title that did it, of course. If Joan had been Mrs Stenning it would all have been plain sailing.

I smiled. “They don’t play bridge,” I said. “Not unless they’re made to. Stenning’s game is poker—he’s a tiger at that. But they won’t want to play cards, and if they did they wouldn’t get the chance. They’ll just sit and talk. Stenning talks about yachts and flying, and Joan talks about water–colours and Cairn terriers.”

She looked up at me despondently. “I don’t know about either. I mean, not to talk to anyone who does. But I do love dogs.”

“That’s good enough,” I said. “Just say that, and Joan’ll talk for hours.”

We got into the car and went back through the town. Mollie wanted to stop and buy a bathing cap, and wanted me to come into the ladies’ outfitters and help her choose it. Dartmouth is a small place and I am quite well known; for many years, of course, my life has been something of a scandal and a byeword in the little town, but always in connection with wine, not women. It took us nearly half an hour to buy that cap and the rest of the things she wanted; by the time we came out and got into the car, Mollie clutching her purchases and laughing with me before all the virtuous housewives of the town, I knew that I had added fresh laurels to my wreath.

We drove up through the town back to my house, left the car on the drive, and went to get our bathing things. Then we went down together through the fuzzy; it was sunny and warm, with the wind somewhere in the south–west so that my beach was in the lee of the cliff. The tide was about half flood; I couldn’t have picked a better day to introduce her to the place.

I gave her the hut to change in, and went and undressed among the trees myself. I was ready long before she was, and I can remember sitting on the rocks in the sun down there waiting for her and wondering how this was going to end. I didn’t get much further with that speculation because I had little experience to guide me; in all my life I had never lived in such intimacy with any girl before. There’s a lot to be said for co–educational schools, I suppose.

She came at last, looking like a coloured picture from a summer magazine. I sat and watched her as she came towards me from the hut, admiring her slim grace. I can see her now.

“That’s an awfully pretty dress,” I said.

She smiled. “I’m glad you like me in it.” Now that wasn’t what I said at all, although I might have done.

She could dive a little, and chose to go in that way, near the beach. I dived in with her on the seaward side; she was a weak swimmer and made straight for the shore. I followed her, and in the shallows we told each other how cold it was. One more dive, and she was ready to go and sit in the sun; I think to her that was the best part of the game. I fetched her towel and we sat on the warm rocks for an hour or more, sun–bathing and watching the small traffic of the harbour mouth, the sparkling sea in the Range, and the white surf around the chequered buoy.

There was a small cloud on the horizon still. She asked:

“Malcolm, when Lady Stenning comes, what ought I to wear? Will the coat and skirt I’ve been wearing be all right?”

I rolled over and looked at her, and grinned. “I’d wear what you’ve got on now, if I were you,” I said. “That suits you best of all.”

She rippled into laughter. “You are awful! I mean, really, what ought I to wear?”

I knew that it would be all right when Joan arrived. “I’d wear something rough and countrified, if you’ve got anything like that,” I said.

She nodded. “I’ve got a terribly old tweed skirt and a jumper, that I had for walking in. Would that be the right thing?” She was very doubtful. “I’ll show it you when we go up.”

I smiled at her. “Just anything you like, so long as it’s not too smart.” She was utterly puzzled. “Don’t make her feel too dirty by comparison. You see, she’s coming down by air—about two and a half hours’ flight in an open machine. She’ll arrive with her face covered in oil, or if it’s not she’ll feel as if it was. She always wants a bath directly she arrives, when they fly down.” I paused. “And anyway, Joan always goes about in the most awful things herself.”

“You don’t think she’ll be dreadfully smart?”

“I don’t think so,” I said.

Chapter 11

I found Fedden very busy with the local police officials. He broke off for a few minutes to have a talk with me, but he could not add much to what he had told me on the telephone. So far as he knew, Gordon had left Gloucester and was now at Scotland Yard. He expected Norman to come down on the next day to assist in the preparations for the arrest of the boat. He accepted my offer of the tug, and I promised to see that she was properly equipped for a long trip. He was not sure in what way he would use her, and would consult with Norman about this.

He was up to his eyes in work, and so I didn’t keep him long. I went on to my yard, and gave instructions for the tug to be filled up with fuel oil and fitted out for a sea passage. Normally her crew consisted of the skipper and the engineer; I didn’t quite know what to do about these men, and told them I would see them the next afternoon.

I was getting more than a little worried over this affair. Stenning’s warning was troubling me a bit, though Billy seemed to be in safety from his associates. I was more concerned over the safety of my own men, the crew of my tug. I had offered the vessel for police use; one could hardly have refused that help. At the time I had not thought about the crew, but obviously the vessel was no use without her crew. If she were used for the arrest of a gun runner I might be sending my skipper and my engineer into some danger if I sent them out with her. I had not thought of that.

By the time that I reached home I had decided that I’d ring up Stenning and see if he could come. I called him up in London, and got through to him in a few minutes. He was free all the next day, and I fixed up with him that he would come down by the early train. I didn’t want him to fly down; it seemed to me that the less attention that was directed to this part of the world the better for us all. I arranged to have the car to meet the train.

Then I rang up the yard and gave instructions that Irene should be got up on the slip at once. That would provide a reason for his visit.

I went to look for Mollie then, and found her with old Robertson in the garden. She had been with him all the afternoon, grubbing about in an old pair of gloves in the herbaceous border; she loved her flowers. As I came near she straightened up, and came and showed me what she’d done while I had been away.

I walked back with her towards the house, and as we went I told her about Billy. I don’t think she was very greatly interested. Throughout the whole of this affair the politics of it made very little difference to her; she was pleased to hear that Billy’s association with an apparently illegal business was coming to an end, but she had no interest in the business itself. She was far more interested in my garden and the traffic of the harbour mouth. She told me that she had seen two steamers coming in.

We went in and had tea together in the library. I was still worried and absorbed in this affair, and talked to her about it for a time, but not with much success. She told me that old Robertson had been telling her about gannets, how they eat so much fish that they can’t fly and go scuttering off along the water when you come near them in a boat. And so I gave it up, content to watch her and to see that she enjoyed herself.

In any case, I was inclined to doubt if anything was going to happen after all. The glass was going slowly down; from a long knowledge of our local conditions it looked to me as if we were in for a spell of continuous bad weather, probably with a gale or two from the south–east. That would be no weather for landing anything upon a beach; it might quite well happen that the whole affair would come to nothing.

But after tea she said a thing that startled me. “I don’t know what they’ll be thinking of me at the Palais,” she said, a little ruefully. “I ought to have gone back there on Sunday, but I can’t till Billy gets right, can I?”

I fumbled mentally for my immature proposal, and put it back again. “I hadn’t thought of that,” I said. “Will they make a lot of bother if you stay a few days more?”

“I don’t know,” she said. “Things are generally pretty slack about this time of year. Of course, they might turn nasty and get somebody else in my place if I stay away.”

I nodded slowly. “You’d have to stay on here if they did that,” I said timidly.

But she said quickly: “Oh, I couldn’t do that,” and I hadn’t the wit to take her up and ask: “Why not?” She added: “I could always get in at Birmingham. Mr Evans said he’d take me on any time if I was out of a job. He’s ever so nice.”

“You needn’t really worry about that,” I said. “We can probably fix up something between us when the time comes, both for you and Billy.”

She looked up at me. “It’s ever so good of you to take this trouble. But we wouldn’t want any money. Only just to get started in a job again.”

I smiled. “Get you a job all right,” I said. “Even if I had to buy a Palais to do it.”

She laughed, and said: “Oh, you are silly.” And then she said: “Just an introduction, like, to somebody you know, would do.”

And so we left it. I went off to write letters feeling I had been a coward. She spent a little of the time before dinner cutting and arranging the flowers she had picked, and for the rest she sat in the model room where I was writing, pretending to read a book but really looking out over the Range at the darkening sea. “It’s ever so different,” she said. “It looks all cold and grey like, now.”

“It’s like that all the winter,” I said absently, from my desk. “You wouldn’t like it down here then.”

She said: “I think I should. It must be lovely when it’s rough.”

The dressing gong went soon after that and we went up to change. I had a fire in the library again that night for it had grown quite cold; when I came down Sixpence was standing before it, stretching out her bare arms to the blaze. She wore the same blue and silver frock that she had worn before. She had said that it was an old one, but as I came into the room and saw her standing there before the fire it seemed to me that she was most beautiful. To me that night she was the loveliest girl I had ever seen in all my life.

I said: “What about a drink?”

We had our cocktails and went in to dine. I had had a fire lit in the dining–room and we had the candles lit; outside in the grey evening the dusk was falling early. That was an intimate dinner that we had that night, and a good one; Rogers had done us well. I ordered up a bottle of the Château Yquem, and we dined merrily; we had nothing to be particularly pleased about, and yet we were very happy in the dining–room. I close my eyes and I can see the gleaming silver and the glass, and see the blue and silver of her frock.

We went through into the library, and sat before the fire with our coffee and liqueur. I suggested that she play a little on the piano, but she wanted to sit by the fire, and so we sat there talking all the evening. She wanted to know about the world, the foreign countries that she’d only seen upon the films. She wanted to know about my early life, about my time in the United States and about the Amazon affair. She wanted to know about dogs and horses, and hunting; she had never ridden a horse.

I sat and told her about all these things, watching the play of the firelight upon her face and neck, and the slim grace of her arms. I told her all about my early life, the things that I had done when I was a boy, the places I had seen, the places that I meant to see before I died. As I sat there talking to her I seemed to slip back through the years; I was no longer a man of middle age, stuck in his own small groove of shipbuilding. I talked to her as if I was a young man starting out on life, wanting to see and to experience all that life could give. She made me feel like that.

She said, a little wistfully: “It would be wonderful to do all that.”

“My dear,” I said, “I want you to.”

It had slipped out before I knew what I was saying, so easy is it when one isn’t bothering. She sat there very quiet in her chair, staring at the fire. I rose and took her hand and drew her to her feet beside me in the firelight while I said my piece.

“I want you to stay here with me,” I said as gently as I could. “This last fortnight has been the happiest I’ve ever had. My dear, I don’t want you to go back to dancing. It was lonely enough down here before you came; God knows it would be lonelier if you went away.” I drew her into my arms. “I mean, I love you, Mollie. That’s a funny sort of thing for an old man like me to say. But it’s true, dear. I want you to stay here for good with me.”

She rubbed her face against my dinner–jacket coat. “Oh, my dear,” she said, quite quietly. That was all.

Ten minutes later she looked up at me, and said: “You mean we’d live down here together, like? Just you and me?”

I bent and kissed her. “That’s right,” I replied. “I want you to stay and marry me as soon as this is all cleared up.”

She said: “To marry you….” And then she drew herself upright in my arms, and said: “Malcolm dear, I want to sit down and talk sensible.”

I let her go, puzzled, and we sat down again upon the chesterfield. She took one of my hands in hers, and held it. “I couldn’t marry you,” she said simply. “It wouldn’t do.”

There was a little silence after she said that; I was attempting to collect myself. I fell to stroking the hand that was holding my own.

“Tell me what’s the matter,” I inquired. “Why wouldn’t it do? I think it would do very well myself.”

She shook her head. “It wouldn’t do,” she repeated, staring into the fire. “I know.”

She turned to me. “I don’t want you to think that this is a surprise to me,” she said quietly, “or that I didn’t know you wanted me. You don’t have to have been in a Palais to know that. And I have thought of what I’d do if you told me, and if you wanted me to marry you.”

I smiled. “So have I,” I said. “This isn’t any snap decision on my part. I’ve been thinking of it for some time. I’d like you to know that.”

She nodded slowly. “Please,” she said, “I want to tell you what I think.”

“Of course,” I said.

She turned away and stared into the fire, but she did not withdraw her hand. “Lots of the girls I’ve been with married fellows who came in to dance,” she said. “And some didn’t, but just went away, and in a year or so they’d be back again, but in some other Palais. And lots of the ones that married, married people in quite good positions, earning a thousand a year, some of them. And it didn’t come out right, not for them. Not ever that I know.”

She glanced at me. “And I always thought that whatever happened to me, I’d not do that.”

I stirred. “You mean that the families made things uncomfortable for them?”

She nodded. “That’s right. They didn’t seem to settle right, and then the men would get going after someone else….” She smiled at me, a little sadly. “Not that I think that you’d go doing that on me.” She turned away again towards the fire. “Some of them just didn’t want anything more than the money, and they got that so they didn’t mind. But it never came out really right—not like one’d want it to be.”

She said: “In the books, and the things you hear about men being dragged down by marrying wrong—they do happen. And the girls that get dragged up by marrying … I believe it’s happier not to be married at all, when it’s like that.”

We sat for a little time in silence after she said that. I was wondering how I could best get over this difficulty, which seemed to be so real to her. But she went on:

“I wouldn’t know what to say to your friends, Colonel Fedden and the rest, and they’d not know what to say to me. They’d think you’d acted awfully funny, marrying like that.”

I drew her to me on the chesterfield. “My dear,” I said, “it wouldn’t be like you think. You’ve met the only member of my family I care two hoots about, and there’s nothing like that about Joan and Stenning, is there? And, my dear, I want you for my wife.”

She sat there by me in the firelight, stroking my hand and looking down on it. “I know you do,” she said at last. “That’s what makes it so difficult.”

She raised her eyes to mine. “I love to think of you wanting me that way,” she said simply. “And what I thought we might do, we might just try it for a bit, and see how it went.” She glanced around. “I don’t mean here. It wouldn’t do, with all your servants and that. But I thought we could go away somewhere for a month or two, where they didn’t know you….

“We could go to Torquay,” she said hopefully, “for a sort of holiday together, like.” She loved that place. She eyed me doubtfully. “Would you like that?”

I wondered absently if King Cophetua had had this sort of thing, and if so, what he did about it. I turned to her and smiled. “We’ll go to Torquay for our honeymoon,” I said, “or for the start of it. But it’s going to be a proper honeymoon for us—no funny business.” I thought about it for a minute. “I’ve never taken girls away for holidays, and I’m too old to learn. You can’t teach an old dog new tricks.”

She laughed. “I believe you’d learn that one all right,” she said.

I shook my head. “Not me—you should start young for that. My dear, that isn’t what I want at all. I want you to marry me in church, and be my wife.”

She stared into the fire. “I don’t know what to say.”

We sat on like that for a long time, talking in little quiet sentences, with great pauses in between. She was distressed that I had turned down her solution to the difficulty, but not, I think, surprised. I could not bring her to agree to marry me. Perhaps if I had been rough with her I might have succeeded, but I couldn’t do that. Each time I tried we came upon the same brick wall.

“Colonel Fedden would think you’d acted awfully funny, marrying like that.” I cursed Fedden heartily that night. To her he represented all the old conservatism of my family. Rather curiously, she said something once about the pictures in the dining–room. I think she had been talking to the servants, or old Robertson: she knew a lot about my family.

We sat there for an hour, or longer it may be, but we got no further. There was something in her attitude which made me curiously humble in my arguments; I could not bully her with any he–man stuff. She had no other thought than for my interest. She was so conscious of the difference in our upbringing, so certain that the marriage wouldn’t do me any good. I could not get her to see my point of view. I could not make her see that for years I have had no friends, that I have lived so much alone that class means very little to me now. It’s different when you’re young and live in a clique of people of your own sort; you live narrow then. But when you get to my age and live by yourself, it’s different. When you’re as lonely as I’ve been you get to value friends for what they are; you get a little broader minded than you used to be.

At last:

“Let’s have a cup of tea,” I said, and rang the bell for Rogers.

She murmured composedly that that would be lovely. She was not upset, or noticeably so. Girls are so much stronger than men are in many ways; that night she sat and talked about this quietly, restrained. And her case was quite clear. She would not bind me with a marriage—that was how she looked at it—till we had lived together for a time.

“People don’t see things right when they’re in love,” she said, a little sadly. “I know.”

Rogers brought the tea, and we sat and drank it as if this evening had been ordinary. I could see no way out of this impasse except with time; in a few days I thought perhaps she’d change her mind, and I could bring her to my point of view. And so when we had drunk our tea I raised her to her feet, and said:

“My dear, I’m not going to worry you, or nag about this any more. Let’s go to bed—and I mean go to bed alone, too.” She smiled at that. “We’ll argue this out later, when this other thing’s all straightened up. But till then, I want you to know that I love you. That … that’s all.”

She took my hand and kissed the back of it. “I don’t know what to say …” she said at last, very softly. And so we stood like that together for a minute till I sent her up to bed.

Next morning I reviewed the situation as I dressed. Stenning was coming down, and would be with me by the afternoon. By the afternoon I expected to hear something of Norman and Billy; I rang up Fedden after breakfast, and found that he did not know when they were likely to arrive. He thought not till nightfall perhaps. He had all arrangements in hand, so that there was plenty of time.

As regards Mollie, there was nothing I could do till this thing was cleared up. I did not think she would go back up North; we had this common ground, at any rate, that it was better for us both to be together. I thought that if I left things for a day or two till the immediate rush of this affair was over it would give her time to think about it, and I hoped that then I should be able to persuade her to my point of view.

If not—well, I should have to come to hers. At the end of our honeymoon, I thought, she’d probably agree to marry me….

I went down to the yard that day and took Mollie with me in the car. They were getting Irene up on the patent slip when I got there; we stood and watched them till the vessel slowly slid up out of the water on the traveller. Mollie was amazed.

“She’s ever such a size underneath the water, isn’t she?” she remarked. “You’d never think!”

I gave instructions for them to start on scraping her; there was nothing the matter with her seams. Then I put Sixpence in a pram and she went paddling around the harbour, while I went into the office and went through my letters; an hour later I went round the yard and had a look at the Sweet Anna’s rudder with old Sammy Gore. His pintles were all right, to his regret I think, but he succeeded in wheedling a lot of unnecessary running gear out of me, and a new stove for the galley.

That took me all the morning. Coming off on to the quay I looked about for Sixpence, and saw the pram alongside Runagate. I took the quay punt and went off to her; she put her head up from the forecastle hatch as I came up alongside. “I’ve been looking at the boat,” she informed me. “It is funny in this little cooking place.”

I dropped down through the hatch beside her in the forecastle. “There’s plenty of room to cook sitting down,” I said. “And anyway, you can reach everything.”

She stared round. “It’s sort of cosy,” she remarked at last. “I never knew ships were like this inside.” She stared through at the bulkheads of the saloon. “All this polished wood….”

We went up through the forehatch and sat upon the bitts for a few minutes, smoking a cigarette. “It’s ever so lovely here,” she said at last. “The ships, and things.”

I blew a cloud, and laughed at her. “You’d better stay here, then,” I said. “It’s up to you!”

She laughed with me. “You must think me ever so soft,” she said.

I shook my head. “I don’t.”

She said: “Don’t let’s talk about it now.” And a little later on she said: “It would be lovely to live here, with the ships and the seabirds, and all.” She turned to me: “Do you know, I feel as if I’d lived here all my life, and my father and mother and all before. Just as if I’d been brought up here….” She sat there staring up the river. “As if I knew what was up there, round the bend, with the river and the sea–shore in the middle of the land, like.”

I nodded slowly. “I expect you do,” I said absently. I knew just what she meant. Where a long estuary runs into the land, an estuary with a rocky bottom, you do get just what she had spoken of—the sea–shore in the middle of the land. Little sandy beaches all among the hayfields and the woods. She knew it all, and yet I had not taken her up there.

We went ashore and got into the car, and drove up to the house. And as we went indoors she said to me:

“Is Lady Stenning coming down this afternoon?”

I shook my head. “Just Philip. Why?”

She turned away. “I think I’d like to have a talk with her,” she said quietly. “She was ever so nice to me.”

I took her hand and smiled at her. “My dear,” I said, “don’t worry about it now. Leave it for a couple of days till this other thing has quieted down, and then we’ll have a talk about it, and you can see her and hear what she has to say.”

“All right,” she said, “if that’s the best.”

I rang up Fedden after lunch and had a talk with him. He told me that Norman was coming down that night with Gordon, in readiness for the events of the following day. He said that they would not arrive till after dark—he thought about eleven o’clock at night. There were to be considerable movements of police in preparation for the landing, and it had been arranged that these movements should take place at night, to obviate the risk of a leakage of information. He asked if Gordon might remain in my house for the time being. He suggested that he should be brought straight there that night.

I said that that would be agreeable to me, and I mentioned to him that Stenning was coming down. I asked him what he wanted done about the tug.

He replied that he could not say definitely what the plans would be till he had had a talk with Norman. Could we arrange about the tug that night, after Norman came?

I frowned. “You mean tonight—after eleven o’clock?”

He said that they would probably be working all night. He had been up most of the previous night, and was going to snatch a little sleep after tea, if possible.

“All right,” I said. “You’d better come up here with him when you send Gordon. You’d better all come up, and talk about it here. You’ve got to bring up Gordon, anyway.”

“That’s very good of you,” he said.

“Not at all. I’ll expect you about half–past eleven, or some time like that?”

He agreed that that would be about the time, and I rang off.

I remember glancing at the barograph as I set down the telephone. It had gone down again and this time rather sharply: in the Range an on–shore wind was getting up.

Stenning arrived a little later in the afternoon, and I took him down to see his vessel on the slip. That was the ostensible purpose of his visit, and I thought it was as well that it should be carried out in full. As we pottered about the yard I told him all that had been going on; I found him intensely interested. He was worried that I had asked the police up to my house, that I had offered to take in Gordon. I expostulated with him over that, and he listened patiently to what I had to say.

“I see your point,” he said at last. “It’s probably as well to have Gordon. But if the police have got to have a meeting they should have it in their own place. I don’t see that you want them in your house particularly.”

We went up to the house and dined with Mollie, changing into dinner jackets. She had been walking in the town that afternoon while we had been away, looking at the shops and exploring the streets and quays. She was especially intrigued by a crew of cadets that she had seen down on the water front, sailing a Navy cutter. She thought they looked ever such nice boys….

And afterwards she sang to us. We sat in the darkened library, Stenning in a chair beside the fire, and Mollie at the piano in a little pool of light. I sat over by her as she played and sang the lyrics that she knew, the dance songs that were folk tunes of the young. We made no pretence. It must have been quite obvious to Stenning that we were deeply in love; he sat apart and puffed at his cigar, and took but little notice of us at the other end of the room. Joan had probably been talking to him and he accepted us for what we may have been—a pair of silly fools behaving as if this had been our first calf love.

Presently she was tired of singing, and we went over to him by the fire. I ordered the whisky and her tea, and we sat drinking this together, chatting of ships and of the flights that he had made, and ventures that he hoped to make. We sat there for a long time talking in that way, till at last we heard a car, and it was Fedden and his crowd.

I took them into the dining–room, as being more suitable for the meeting that we had to hold. I had had a few sandwiches and whisky placed upon the table, and a writing pad. The room was brightly lit. The curtains were drawn over the east window looking out over the harbour mouth, but the alcove with the oriel north window was uncurtained. That window looks out on to the north lawn.

There was Fedden and Norman and a police superintendent that they had brought with them, Gordon, and Mollie, and myself, and Stenning. We started the proceedings with a drink, standing beside the table before sitting down. I was with Stenning and Norman, talking to Fedden; Mollie and her brother were a little way apart.

Till Norman put his glass down, and remarked: “I think we’d better get to work.”